<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://cosmologyluke.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://cosmologyluke.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-05T14:03:21+00:00</updated><id>https://cosmologyluke.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Luke Hart&apos;s website
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">chester marathon 2022</title><link href="https://cosmologyluke.github.io/blog/2022/chester/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="chester marathon 2022" /><published>2022-12-30T15:06:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-30T15:06:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cosmologyluke.github.io/blog/2022/chester</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cosmologyluke.github.io/blog/2022/chester/"><![CDATA[<p>Here we are again. You’d be forgiven for thinking I actually enjoyed doing them at this point, but this time around I decided to do <em>Chester</em> marathon. This was the first of my dips into serious marathons that actually featured a little bit of a hill in them. Chester runs out into the middle of Cheshire, does a few ebbs and flows and back into the city’s perimeter for a final dash along the River Dee. Seemed reasonable enough so why not?</p>

<h3 id="training">Training</h3>
<p>So the training for this one was much the same as Manchester except work/life had gotten considerably more busy. For example, we were purchasing our first house and preparing lots of other things in our little lives. But even with that, I still found the time to do many big runs and get ready for the big day. This also coincided with many of the final <em>Liverpool Running Bugs</em> races as part of the 2022 championship. I also took upon myself the challenge of completing 50 Parkruns in 1 year which was a much harder feat than simply turning up, due to many logistical reasons. The nicest part of this particular race was that I would not be alone… Tim, my future father-in-law also decided to run his first marathon with me and that was brilliant. It meant that we could discuss training, dos and don’ts and other marathon related topics. Of course, I already knew that this race would be a lot harder than any of the others.</p>

<p>The training itself consisted of much the same; Monday 10ks, 5k on Saturday, and then varying the distance as we approached the big day. I noticed that my longer, slow runs became more frequent in this particular cycle. That was both a good thing and a bad thing. It was good because it meant that I felt a little bit fresher on the whole, however I will get to the bad later. It was still really difficult juggling the Chester run due to work and the constant shifts of trains. Here in the United Kingdom, for context, many of the trains were frequently cancelled or delayed hugely. The train companies have been acting at less than optimum capacity but mostly, there have been train strikes going on. I will not make this a political blog post and discuss that as those close to me know my feelings on this; but, that is by the by. Long story short, getting to and from work has been very inconsistent and made running training very difficult. But it still allowed me to run 16-20 milers at a lower pace.</p>

<p>One of the key differences this time has been that I contracted COVID a month before the marathon. This made very little difference to me as I started back training as soon as I was well enough; yet the first half marathon training run after the incident was quite exhausting. But all in all, there was a really good build up to the big day.</p>

<h2 id="taper">Taper</h2>
<p>This may have been a big problem with the way I prepared for Chester. I reverted back to the 4 week taper for London whereas I probably should have used a stricter taper on the two weeks before, like in Manchester. The conclusion: so many weeks of taper made it more difficult to appropriately lower down the intensity which led to fast runs in the last week. But this could just be conjecture: either way, the taper was a longer one than usual but the drop in intensity was not done correctly, in my opinion.</p>

<h2 id="marathon">Marathon</h2>
<p>So we get to it on the October 2022, the London Marathon is running the same day as the Chester Marathon this year (<em>ah happier times</em>). Except this time, we get to the run a day early and we book a hotel the day before and about 400m away from the start. So in theory, this is a less stressful start than both the other 2. We loaded up on pasta and went for sleep, prepared ourselves for the next day. As Sunday starts, we get ourselves down to the start area at Chester Racecourse. For this of course we needed a small breakfast, little bits of extra energy and a healthy addition of water. Then we loaded into the area, it was clear but particularly crisp and cold when we got on the racecourse. And then when the time was right, no drama, no extra theatrics - we got going. Tim and I both started off relatively well but he fell into the 4 hour pacing while I tried to keep as close as I could to the 3 hour 30 pacing. Now, this is a very brave approach to the pacing, since it is 10 minutes off my previous but I felt confident going into the race and it seemed like a sensible target. The first 5-10k was uneventful and I could feel myself easing into the 8 minute mile pace. I stuck with the pace runner as best as I could, but he decided to start off particularly fast so we honestly struggled at the start but settled into a much more reasonable constant pace after a few kilometres. Then, I stuck at this pace relatively well and even headed the pacers for a while. At around 8k, I met a lad called Ian and he was a runner with the <em>Whitchurch Whippets</em>. Ian was fantastically motivational, had a brilliant sense of humour and found the run as intense as I did. However I daresay, he is a far better runner as time will tell.</p>

<p>As we passed the 10 mile mark, I could feel a bit of lag in my legs but my chest felt good. I knew I had run a good 10 miles well, but I felt like lots was left. This even held true until the half marathon mark: I knew I had held the pace alright. However, once we hit around 25-28k I felt that something was different and by the 20 mile mark something was very much so. My legs were going okay but the fatigue, due to the improper downing of intensity, had led to a weirder form where I think I was really inefficient in my running. So much so that by 34k, I was absolutely shattered and had fallen off the 8 minute mile pace. Ian had done the same but was still pulling away - I had to ease off and leave him ahead. It was a slog. Finishing the marathon just seemed to become almost impossible because of what I know believed was overpacing. Even though it hasn’t been that much faster on the day, the previous day’s parkrun, everything else: it was all adding up. Therefore, I calmed it down and slowed down and eventually, over the horizon I could see Chester. As we approached we realised that we were using the same trail back into the city; however there was a big hill up into the southern part of the city first. This was where I pushed all my remaining energy and then managed to slip my way across the final path along the River Dee into the finish line. Finally, done.</p>

<p>That marathon will hit the most of the 3 purely because it was the hardest and the only one where the thought crossed my mind not to finish. It was heartbreaking even to think it. But the good news is that my training is a bit more reasonable now, I have learned from the situation and I intend not to allow a similar thing to happen again.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <img height="500" width="340" class="img-fluid rounded" title="Chester Finishing Picture I" src="/assets/img/chesterA.jpg" />
    </div>
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <img height="500" width="340" class="img-fluid rounded" title="Chester Finishing Picture II" src="/assets/img/chesterB.jpg" />
    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
At the finish of the Chester Marathon 2022: 3 marathons in 2 years
</div>

<p>So to sum up:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Finished Chester</li>
  <li>Bit slower than before</li>
  <li>First time I hit the wall hard on a marathon - probably ran the first 25km too fast</li>
  <li>Lessons learned, just another training</li>
</ul>

<p>Next up is the Manchester 2 Liverpool 50 mile in 2023. For ultra-marathons, I think even more discipline is required so lets see if I can keep up!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[hills and savaged]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">manchester marathon 2022</title><link href="https://cosmologyluke.github.io/blog/2022/manchester/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="manchester marathon 2022" /><published>2022-04-11T22:06:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-11T22:06:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cosmologyluke.github.io/blog/2022/manchester</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cosmologyluke.github.io/blog/2022/manchester/"><![CDATA[<p>So, several months have passed since I <a href="/blog/2021/london">ran the London marathon</a> and there was a small part of me that thought it was a swansong to tick a box on the bucket list. But the next week, I had registered for the <em>Therme Manchester Marathon 2022</em>. My discipline for London was fantastic: my diet was amazing, I drank so much water and I regularly trained lots of different distances. Unfortunately, this was not to be the same for the April beast before me.</p>

<h3 id="training">Training</h3>
<p>Like before, we start with the training. Truth be told between October and April I never quite reached the 50 mile weeks I did before. I got close but never hit those targets. But I was confident this wasn’t the biggest problem in the world: I was months into a very intense new job (which I love by the way!), lots of important life decisions in the pipeline and lots of catching up to do post-COVID (I know that COVID has not gone, I’m not naive, but I had lots of time away from family over the lockdowns and within precautions, really had some catching up to do…).</p>

<p>The main thing is the distances: I shunned away from the compulsory &gt;21km per week. Most weeks I did a half, a 16 miler or even a 20 miler in a couple of cases, but I wasn’t as strict about forcing one out each week. There were some really exciting runs: particularly one where I ran down to Styal and Wilmslow in abysmal rainy weather, where the River Mersey and River Dean nearly broke their banks! But also Emma and I joined a running club: the <a href="https://liverpoolrunningbugs.wixsite.com/bugs">Liverpool Running Bugs</a>. You can see the photo of myself and lots of the bugs at a parkrun in Manchester a few months ago! With the bad weather and short patches of nice weather, I focussed more on the shorter distances, driving my 5k time below 20 minutes for the first time at Christmas and peaking at 19:45 for 5k in March. But I still did 30 milers, 17 milers and lots of slower halfs just to keep used to the higher distances.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <img height="500" width="340" class="img-fluid rounded" title="Floods on the river Mersey by Styal" src="/assets/img/floods_mersey.jpg" />
    </div>
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <img height="500" width="340" class="img-fluid rounded" title="Liverpool Running Bugs: Alexandra Parkrun" src="/assets/img/bugs_parkrun.jpg" />
    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
Left: The River Mersey creeping up the banks as I was running to Styal.<br /> Right: The <em>Liverpool Running Bugs</em> who came to South Manchester for a lovely parkrun, two weeks before the Manchester Marathon.
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="taper">Taper</h2>
<p>Taper this time round was a 2 week job. I finished a fortnight before the race on 63km for the week. For the first down week, I dropped to 43km and for the second week I dropped to 25km. This was obviously followed by the Sunday 42km the same week. But this taper was actually nicer and easier, had my legs been already conditioned and less tired going into the taper. I think I prefer the 2 week taper model by dropping 25% the first week and 50% the second week. Much easier taper period compared to London.</p>

<h2 id="marathon">Marathon</h2>
<p>To prep myself for the marathon, I ran the Fletcher Moss parkrun on Saturday 2 April 2022 in an effort to condition myself to marathon pace and hopefully get around in 26 minutes. I actually finished just over 24 minutes and that was a damning indictmnet for my laissez-faire attitude the next day. It was a much easier commute to the start all round this time: tram to Trafford Bar, walk up the road, mull around for 10-30 minutes and then casually walk up to the start lane on Chester Road. It was here that I ditched my very old Primark jumper that had kept me warm, the sun proceeded to beam out and I stretched prepped, and checked all the spots. I had 3 gels, electrolytes and water and felt pumped. First time sporting the <em>Running Bugs</em> jersey to a big race! WE WERE OFF! I started the race in a similar vein to London: swept up in the euphoria of it all, slightly faster than intended. This was within known parameters though. I started at the front of the Orange A Wave, spotting several runners pull ahead at a much faster than the 4h pace we had all predicted for ourselves. I did not get carried away (yet) and stayed comfortably near 5:00/km pace, an optimistic pace I had set myself. As we turned towards the lower parts of Trafford, or the upper parts of Stretford and Chorlton, it dawned on me that I had not been as talkative for this race, I was not chatting with random runners excited for the future and I did not find a buddy to cling to for pace. The eager and positive 4h-pace Luke of October last year seemed a sad bygone time. But I was a source of laughter after 2 mile as I pulled up, stripped quickly, removed and chucked my thermal layers: it was far too hot for thermals…</p>

<p>Half an hour in, roughly 5-6km and the consistency was reassuring. I was running very stable but actually pushing into under 5:00/km territory. In October and November, I had done this at a much faster pace for both Alton Towers (1h 40) and Aintree half marathons (1h 37m) respectively - but I still knew it was stupid to expect the same from this distance. I had once tried this with 27km and survived the wall by the skin of my teeth: in that I did not hit it until 26.6 km… So I was very cautiously optimistic. The City Centre leg didn’t help as the atmosphere was palpable, exciting, everyone was cheering and it was fantastic. Something bittersweet about that atmosphere digs on me and I will mention it towards the end. But for now, everything was great: Emma had tram-hopped to spot me on the way into and out of Deansgate, the tram-hopping a feature of the day! Now we turned back up Trafford and onto Chester Road for the long gruelling journey to Altrincham. I say long and gruelling but it was not really that way until after we got there. A happy side note: former American Football coach Pete Birds was running towards City Centre as I passed, part of the Orange B wave. Pete has done an exceptional job over the last year getting fit for marathon distance and spoiler alert - he absolutely smashed it!</p>

<p>Chester Road is really long. It stretches from the outside of Deansgate, down through Stretford and Sale all the way to Altrincham. Along this road we saw lots of crowds at Sale with some in between as well. The course veered towards Timperley and that is where I remember the first red flags. Twinges in hamstrings. It was all manageable and within known long distance parameters so it didn’t alarm me; but it was still worrying this had happened just as we hit the half marathon mark. I looked at my watch: 1h 43m. I had absolutely surged the first half. No panic yet, but I knew this wasn’t going to be easy now. As Altrincham beckoned, I remember the hill over the train lines into the town centre and it was a slog. This was 16 miles - 10 to go.</p>

<p>On the turnaround from Altrincham something changed. I ran part way back up the road towards Timperley and a switch flicked on. Meter just went to empty with no warning. Minutes before I had a gel but I knew there would be a lull before that energy came. Mercy me: when they say you hit the wall, you hit the wall. Bizarrely however, because I had a sugar rush and then a big jump down again, I technically hit it twice at 21 mile and 23 mile. I remember seeing Emma (bless her for following me) at Sale and even though I was all smiles, it was not as well managed as London. I knew I had to just hold on. The longer this dragged on, the more everything would eat me up. So after around 37km, I pushed past the wall and my legs gave me a little bit back. 5km remaining and in my mind, the clock was ticking. I knew I had a parkrun left but also knew I had to finish as soon as possible. We surge up Seymour Grove, past lots of nice houses with trees creeping half way across the roads from height, providing a small amount of relief from the now, cruel sun. Up ahead I saw the mile markers tumble slower and slower. But I managed to keep into 5:something pace. Finally we turned and I could see Trafford Bar. This was it. I dug in and pushed on for the finish. Look at the watch: 200m to go, 3h 38m 40s. I could not believe it. I couldn’t really tell you what happened when I finished other than a blur of yoga mats, trying to eat a disgusting SIS protein bar (sorry SIS, stick to gels) and drinking a Erdinger alcohol free beer with isotonics that was actually weirdly nice. It took a good 2 hours to come back to reality because my head was just so out of it.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
  <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
      <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/manc_mara.png" alt="" title="Manchester marathon finishing picture" style="width:90%" />
  </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
  Picture at the finish. Don't let the smile fool you... I did not know what day it was.
</div>

<p>It was a marvellous day and I really enjoyed the Manchester marathon but a couple of comments. It really cannot be as flat as they say. There were so many more up and down bits than London, and no it wasn’t just the tired talking, I do not remember being on so many gradients in London. It just isn’t flat. Secondly, the atmosphere was good but I think London spoiled me. Of course a city of 9 million is going to bring more crowds than a city of half a million and Manchester is my home and my heart; but it just felt like we were running out into the sticks of Manchester, the suburbs. Other than the City Centre, Old Trafford and at a push, Altrincham, at no point was the support really on a level that it dramatically lifted me up. It is not like Manchester is not capable of it: the Great Manchester half marathon, that runs across Mancunian way, that is an amazing atmosphere and I always love running it (excited to do it this year!) So to sum up:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Finished the Manchester Marathon</li>
  <li>03:39:22</li>
  <li>Word to the wise: if you’re worried about your pace in a marathon, <strong>do not overcompensate</strong> (thank me later)</li>
  <li>Somehow pesto and pasta the night before means PBs</li>
  <li>See you all at Chester in October!</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[yikes, did another one]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">london marathon 2021</title><link href="https://cosmologyluke.github.io/blog/2021/london/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="london marathon 2021" /><published>2021-11-05T09:07:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-05T09:07:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cosmologyluke.github.io/blog/2021/london</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cosmologyluke.github.io/blog/2021/london/"><![CDATA[<p>In February 2021, I (<em>convinced by Amy Suddards and David Whitworth who are wonderful people</em>) decided to run the London Marathon for <a href="https://nomancampaign.org">NOMAN</a>. This was partly for myself but mostly because NOMAN are a fantastic charity that undertake big sporting tasks in order to raise money for the <em>HPV and Anal Cancer Foundation</em> in efforts to vaccinate as many people as possible against HPV.</p>

<h3 id="training">Training</h3>
<p>From the first day early in 2021, I was already running. Christmas had been a quiet training period but I had made a promise to pick up <strong>50km</strong> weeks again as soon as January. Over the course of winter turning into spring, my distances picked up to 60-70km and included more and more 20 mile runs, with the odd injury-scare here and there. Ankles would hurt for a day, laid off the running, back to normal and back to training. Eventually, as March and April came around I was averaging 70 and eventually 80-85 km a week running, usually with a big run on Sundays. It became everything I did and all I could think about; but remained the vehicle to keep my mental health positive.</p>

<p>Finally, summer dwindled on, the heatwaves, new job and other distractions but the training kept going on. From starting to run during lockdown in March 2020 until December 2020, I had run just over 1000km. By September 2021, I had run 2500km for the year already.</p>

<h3 id="taper">Taper</h3>
<p>Any runner will know that a big part of any training is the preparation and planning - this is even more true for tapering. So over the few weeks before the London Marathon, the volume was reduced to 60km and 10km down every week until the marathon (4 weeks before). I felt a bit weird, like I had too much energy, but it eventually worked out for the best, especially coupled with whole grains, hearty carbohydrates and lots of protein the week before.</p>

<h3 id="marathon">Marathon</h3>
<p>On 3rd October, it was go. Tube to Bank, DLR to Greenwich and a daunting walk through bits of Greenwich Park to the start line. The entrance area felt like a festival with so many people, massive radio towers and lots of music in the background. But instead of background music awaiting the headline act, it was the buffer for us to prepare to move in our droves towards the wave areas that would unleash us onto the 2021 London Marathon course. I chatted with a few people, one man had raised money for <em>Shelter</em> the homelessness charity, another was raising money for the <em>Royal British Legion</em>. A man named Andy from Portsmouth was raising money for <em>Pancreatic Cancer UK</em> in honour of his mum who had passed away. Andy and I would end up running the first 8k together. I found out he had raised nearly <strong>£5000</strong> for the charity afterwards. As our wave progressed to the start and we were at the line, they fired the horn and off we went. 26.2 miles into the unknown. I had trained with several 20 milers, even two 21 milers, but there was about 5 miles of unknown territory that both excited and terrified me. The mission was to hit 4 hours and keep running the whole time.</p>

<p>Andy stayed with me for the first 45 minutes of this journey. We passed countless children offering sweets, bands playing and hype-men running alongside us. Eventually Andy would slow down for his go-to running gel and beckoned me to run on, and so I did. It dawned on about 12-13 km into the race that I was well above the target pace for a 4h finish. I was a bit too excited but I wasn’t na"{i}ve enough to think that I could get away with this the whole journey. We passed all the amazing sights, Woolwich Arsenal, Tower Bridge (where I saw Emma and Uncle Dave in the video you can see in my Twitter below), and parts of the Embankment of the Thames. And so 10 miles of the 26 were like this: moderately cautious, faster than anticipated, loving every minute. After 10 miles, the crowds still strong, I stuck my pace into neutral and tried to maintain as far as I could closer to Canary Wharf. This part of the race is a blur because I was hyper-focussed on numbers and pace. The Isle of Dogs is notoriously solemn and less people are around so you really have to focus up and drive. But that didn’t last long as Canary Wharf, a portion of the race I had been warned about as you strike the 16-17 mile mark and crowds could wane, was absolutely heaving with support, some even over the top of the tunnels close to the Colonnade. This spurred me on to keep with my pace, remembering my training, and that I had hit just slower than this pace on my last, hilly 20 mile run to Disley on the edge of the Peak District.</p>

<div class="jekyll-twitter-plugin"><p>There was a 'Forbidden' error fetching URL: 'https://twitter.com/cosmologyluke/status/1444985163025375233'</p></div>

<p>Finally we hit the problem areas. 4 miles left, coming down the ‘home straight’ towards the centre of London and though I felt good, my legs started to flag. 22 miles and my ankles wanted to acutely let me know they were <strong>not happy</strong> with the current proceedings. I pushed through a mile and felt my will flicker for a second, until under the massive 23 miler pillar stuck out the head of my wonderful Uncle David, who had come over from Tower Bridge to cheer me on again (obviously accompanied by my equally wonderful fianc'{e}e Emma). They screamed that I had ‘got this’ and that was the boost I needed, better than any gel, any sip of water or any type of dope! It is no wonder people run these races with big crowds. Eventually even that push subsided as the leafy streets leading up to the edge of the Mall were starting to wear thin. After 23 miles almost <em>everyone</em> around me had begun walk-running so it immediately became a human obstacle course. I still pushed on but my pace dropped a bit as my hamstrings had started filing complaints about this run as well. Eventually we see 1.0km left and lo-and-behold: I hit the wall. The last km was the longest kilometre of running in my life and thank goodness I had eaten well, had my gels, got extra water along the way, all the above. I felt as though my stomach and chest were about to scream through my ribs but I kept on. I could not make out the various signs telling me 600,400,200 meters left but I kept on. And then we finished:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Finished the London Marathon.</li>
  <li>03:47:01.</li>
  <li>Tick something off the bucket list.</li>
  <li>Fantastic heavy medal.</li>
  <li>Epsom salt bath.</li>
  <li>Watch out every carb in my uncle’s house.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>Since this marathon, I have submitted to the London 2022 ballot, signed up for Manchester 2022, potentially signing up for Chester 2022 (if London is a miss) and I really want to build conditioning to the <em>Manchester 2 Liverpool Ultra</em> for 2023. Running has gone from a get-out clause, to a mental health handicap, to an obsession, to part of mine and my family’s life. It has both saved and trapped me, but there are worse things to spend hours worrying about. For now, I will appreciate every smaller run of 10K or less, because I still remember what it’s like to contend with 4 in one go!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[yup, i ran the london marathon]]></summary></entry></feed>